A Guide to the Richard Byrd Kennon Papers, 1863-1865
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Richard Byrd Kennon Papers, 1863-1865
The Library of Virginia
22744
7 leaves and 26 pages
Richard Byrd Kennon
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift, 8 October 1947, of Clara Vernon Kennon, Valentine, Virginia.
Biographical Information
Richard Byrd Kennon was born 10 November 1835 in Norfolk, Virginia, to George Tarry Kennon (1788-1855) and Ann Whittle Boush Kennon (1796-1864). He married Louisiana Barraud Cocke (1838-1914), and they had 10 children. They resided at "Pea Hill", Brunswick County, Virginia. Kennon served as a 1st Lieutenant in the 4th Virginia Cavalry, Company I, a Captain in the 11th Virginia Cavalry, a Captain and Assistant Adjutant's General in Dearing's Brigade, and an Adjutant in the 8th Virginia Cavalry. These papers also prove his service to Rosser's Brigade; although, Confederate record books contain no record of his participation in the unit. In June 1890, he entered a soldiers' home in Richmond. Kennon died 14 December 1892 at "Pea Hill," and is buried in St. Luke's Episcopal Church cemetery in Northampton County, North Carolina.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1863-1865, of Richard Byrd Kennon (1835-1892) of Brunswick County, Virginia, consisting of military orders concerning Kennon's reassignment, General Thomas L. Rosser's brigade and soldiers in it, and General Robert E. Lee's (1807-1870) General Order No. 9 concerning the surrender of the Army of Northern Virginia; correspondence concerning supplies and corn for Rosser's brigade and reports denying damage done by the brigade to civilian property; a military pass issued to Kennon; a report by Kennon as assistant inspector general of inspection of Rosser's brigade; a map of military positions in Hanover County, Virginia: and a letter from Douglas Southall Freeman (1886-1953) of Richmond, Virginia, to Clara Vernon Kennon (1878-1963) of Brunswick County, Virginia, concerning this map.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Richard Byrd Kennon Papers, 1861-1921 (LVA accessions 14021-14026).
Related Material
Richard Byrd Kennon Papers, 1863-1865 (LVA accession 22995).
Contents List
- Special orders number 91, 19 May 1863, signed by General Henry Heth (1825-1899), relieving Colonel Walter Hanson Jenifer (d. 1878) and Lieutenant Richard Byrd Kennon of duty and ordering them to report to Richmond, Virginia, for reassignment.
- Telegram, 25 ? 1864, from General Jeb Stuart (1833-1864) to General Thomas L. Rosser (1836-1910), ordering his cavalry command to Waynesboro, Virginia.
- Letter, 28 March 1864, from John Taylor (1825-1904) of Hanover County, Virginia, to Kennon stating that he knows of no destruction of property in his neighborhood by Rosser's brigade.
- Pass, 24 March 1864, for Kennon to travel to Orange Court House, Virginia.
- Letter, 28 March 1864, from J. T. Dickinson to General Rosser concerning supplies.
- Telegram, 23 April 1864, from W. B. Richards of Orange County, Virginia, to General Rosser informing him that corn is being sent.
- Orders, 25 July 1864, from H. B. McClellan (1840-1904) to Thomas Estep (d. ca. 1864) of the 12th Virginia Cavalry.
- Orders, 28 August 1864, from H. B. McClellan to M. (Nason) Will of the 12th Virginia Cavalry.
- Report, 31 October 1864, by Kennon as assistant inspector general of inspection of Rosser's Brigade.
- General Order No. 9, 10 April 1865, of Robert E. Lee (1807-1870) to the Army of Northern Virginia informing its soldiers they are surrendered.
- map, no date, of military positions in Hanover County.
- Letter, 10 October 1928, from Douglas Southall Freeman (1886-1953) of Richmond to Clara Vernon Kennon (1878-1963) of Brunswick County, Virginia, concerning the map.